João Vitor de Oliveira

contatovitordeoliveira@gmail.com

linkedin.com/in/contatojoaovitordeoliveira

Summary

Data Engineer and Developer with experience in cloud computing (AWS, GCP), development and maintenance of pipelines for ingestion, transformation and load to Data Lake and Data Warehouse using S3, EMR, PySpark, SQL Server, Apache Nifi, Airflow and data extraction to Tableau. Experience with Back End (Java, SpringBoot), data analysis and manipulation with Python. Passionate about technologies, machine learning, IoT and embedded systems (Raspberry Pi, Arduino).

Experience

Principal Engineer

Blue Avenir GmbH

Jul 2022 - Present (3 months +)

I'm responsible to create, implement and operate end-to-end cloud architectures from differents products of the company, also going through market analysis, gathering requirements with the business and presenting to future clients.

Skills: Python (Programming Language) · Cloud Computing · System Architecture · Soft Skills · Product Management · Product Development

Senior Data Engineer

Blue Avenir GmbH

Oct 2021 - Present (1 year +)

I'm responsible to define, implementing, and managing all end-to-end data processes in the cloud/on-premises, feed data and maintain a reliable infrastructure to our Al solutions, provide technical guide and visibility of our solutions to the business and create new products to deliver value to our clients. Python, GCP, Dremio, Docker, Terraform, Nifi, Github Actions, IONOS

Senior Data Engineer

MovilePay

Apr 2021 - Mar 2022 (1 year)

Building a datalake and datawarehouse from scratch on AWS, responsable of the architecture and leadership using tools such as:

Databrick, Spark, Kafka, Airflow, Terraform, Nifi, Snowflake, Gitlab CI-CD, Metabase



Data Engineer

Inter

Apr 2020 - Apr 2021 (1 year 1 month)

Architecture and maintenance of pipelines for ingestion, transformation and large data load to Data Lake and Data Warehouse using AWS, Spark using the Python API PySpark, SQL Server, Hadoop Ecosystem, Apache Nifi and data extraction for Tableau.

Backend Engineer

Inter

Aug 2019 - Apr 2020 (9 months)

At Banco Inter I work with the Mobile Backend and InternetBank maintenance, monolithic fix and break in microservices using Java language and Spring Boot framework. With 100% cloud application We use AWS solutions for deploying, storing and monitoring logs.

Java, Spring Boot, AWS, Kubernetes, Terraform, GitLab.

Data Engineer

Avenue Code

Jun 2019 - Sep 2019 (4 months)

I'm part of the AC-Forecast Project wich is based on the ETL Integration (Extract, Transform, Load) of data to be consumed by the machine learning algorithms for predictions of the future based on past and present data of AC clients and most commonly by analysis of trends.

The activities are the extraction, the transformation and the consumed of the data, creation jobs at Google Cloud to perform automatic processes and schedule and monitor workflows with AirFlow.

Scala, Python, Spark, Hadoop and Google Cloud

Software Developer

Avenue Code

May 2019 - Sep 2019 (5 months)

Development and maintenance of web application and ETL process from an international warranty service provider company using Python and Java, PostgreSQL database, also using Jenkins for deployment, Github for versionament and Docker for microservices on the workflow.

FITec Developer

Fundação para Inovações Tecnológicas - FITec

May 2018 - Mar 2019 (11 months)

Experience in developing a Business Support System (BSS) in partnership with Ericsson. It is a telecom billing and billing system developed by teams in Brazil, India, Canada and Sweden.

The technologies used are: Python, Java, Jenkins (for continuous integration), Pyteste and JUnit (for automated unit and functional testing).), Gerrit (for versioning and code revisions), Camunda (for BPM modeling and execution).

The Scrum agile development methodology and knowledge sharing between national and international teams using the English language as the official language is used.

Freelancer Mobile Developer

Freelance

Feb 2015 - Jan 2019 (4 years)

Freelancer Mobile Developer publishing and distributing apps on Google PlayStore.

My page: https://play.google.com/store/apps/dev?id=5684499859584473015

Education

Centro Universitário UNA

Bachelor's degree, Computer Engineering 2016 - 2020

xpe IGTI

Machine Learning Analyst , Artificial Intelligence 2020 - 2020 Hands-on Bootcamp from IGTI

Udacity

Data Product Manager, Information Technology 2021 - 2021

Leverage market data to amplify product development. Learn how to apply data science techniques, data engineering processes, and market experimentation tests to deliver customized product experiences. Begin by leveraging the power of SQL and Tableau to inform product strategy. Then, develop data pipelines and warehousing strategies that prepare data collected from a product for robust analysis. Finally, learn techniques for evaluating the data from live products, including how to design and execute various A/B and multivariate tests to shape the next iteration of a product.

Licenses & Certifications

- Coogle Cloud on Coursera Google
- **G** Specialization on Developing Applications with Google Cloud Platform Google
- AWS Solutions Architect Associate (SAA) Amazon Web Services (AWS)
 Issued Jan 2020 Expires Jan 2023
 BMBGSKDKFFBE1Q5M
- Introduction to Amazon Kinesis Data Analytics for Java Applications Amazon Web Services (AWS)
- Deep Dive into Concepts and Tools for Analyzing Streaming Data on AWS Amazon Web Services (AWS)
- Best Practices for Data Warehousing with Amazon Redshift Amazon Web Services (AWS)

- Amazon Redshift Service Primer Amazon Web Services (AWS)
- AWS Hadoop Fundamentals Amazon Web Services (AWS)
- Introduction to Amazon Elastic MapReduce (EMR) Amazon Web Services (AWS)
- Data Engineer with Python Track DataCamp
- Scrum Foundation Professional Certificate CertiProf Issued Aug 2020 Expires Aug 2022
- (A Astronomer Certification for Apache Airflow Fundamentals Astronomer

Skills

Java • JavaScript • Serviços RESTful • Big data • Microcontrollers • Engineering • Apache Spark • Python (Programming Language) • Machine Learning • Amazon Web Services (AWS)

Honors & Awards

Data Engineering, Big Data, and Machine Learning on GCP Specialization - Google
Jul 2019